hey guys welcome to concept and coding
and this is Shan and today we are going
to do the next topic of spring boot that
is Mayan right this is you can say that
the most underestimated topic we
generally think it's just mostly MAV do
build generation nothing much more than
that but today I will show you what all
things Mayan can do why it is very
important to know about May one and how
it makes our developer life easy okay so
let's start with the newest Topic in
springboard that is Mayan so mayavan is
a project management tool not just build
management tool or build generation tool
no it's a project management tool which
helps developer with build generation so
it's just a one part of it right also
dependency resolution documentation and
there are lot many other functionality
which mavens provide Okay so
so Mayan uses pal project object model
to achieve this so whenever we give M
Command right let's say
Mayan M uh
install May one you can say that there
are another comp deploy we will go
through this commands but whenever what
I'm trying to say whenever we give this
commands to Mayan what Mayan first do is
it look for pom.xml in the current
directory from the directory currently
you are running this command so it looks
for pom.xml and then try to look for the
configuration what it has to do with
this okay so Mayan is highly dependent
you can say that p. XML
okay so if you remember before Mayan
there is something called Ant which was
very very popular okay so in the
end we have to tell generally what to
do and how to
do in May one generally we have to only
tell what to
do what to do how to do that's now Mayan
is taking care of Mayan knows that okay
you only tell me what to do how to do I
will take care of it for example we have
given this command mavan install for
example now we tell mavan what to do
okay you have to install how I haven't
tell now that Mayan will take care of it
what okay you have tell me what you have
to do now how to do it that Mayan will
achieve in ear we have to tell what to
do and also how to do it we have to
provide the step sequence of steps to
achieve what we have to do okay so so
advantage of it is uh mavan is that it
simplifies the developer with various
tasks like build generation dependency
resolution documentation and lot more
things and
also it only we have to provide what to
do to it right what task we have to do
how that MAV take care of it okay clear
like what's the advantage MAV provide
why MAV exists right so if you remember
this is is the May project structure
which it follows okay and if you
remember in the previous video where we
have uh downloaded or set up the spring
boot uh project and we have selected the
Mayan so this project got uh downloaded
right with one class spring boot
application in this
package uh learning is spring boot this
is our uh the app name which we give and
and Source main Java and this is what we
provided into the uh group ID artifact
if you remember so this is the package
how the Mayan follows and there would be
one pom.xml
so this is what generally Mayan project
structure is so whatever your app name
is it will first create its directory
then in the main directory itself you
will have
form okay then there you have source
main
Java okay so Source main Java and there
you provided in the spring boot we have
provided this
three right so it create a package like
this com concept and coding learning
springboard this three things we have
provided while creating a spring board
project if you remember and this is one
Java application class it will create
like
this okay and here if you see in the
source p you will find one package of
test and then the same Java com and the
same name the same project structure and
it's equivalent test
class right so this is generally
unit test cases where we will write in
this class for this for this Java class
we will write unit test cases in this
okay so here if you see that we have
sour uh
Source they have test in parallel the
same Java com concept coding learning
springboard and springboard application
test okay so this is the project
structure for may1 which generally
follows and that's why you see this kind
of structure when we downloaded the
project from the spring boot using M if
you have selected grd might be some
other structure got downloaded which grd
supports but for MAV this is the project
structure which MAV
supports okay now when the project got
downloaded right so this pom.xml we got
right so the same pom.xml I have copied
here and I will show you what exactly it
is like how to read this pom.xml what
generally the meaning of each properties
and elements defined here okay so here
if you see the first
part
this
project okay this first part what here
you will see certain kind of schema
schema location okay so what is it it is
specify the XML
schema also make sure that our XML
adhere to the correct structure and
version defined by the May
one so whatever the XML you can say that
the rules it has provided in this schema
this should be the name okay inside this
parent you can have group ID artifact
version only you can't by default use
hey can I write this uh here something
XY
Z XY Z close can I do something no it is
this XY Z is not defined in the schema
of the parent inside this so we can't
write something like randomly it has to
follow properly what in within this
element what all things can we write
right so it should follow certain schema
here if you see the parent
part this
one this is used to define the parent
project the project if you remember
which we have downloaded from Spring
boot right so the Palm which we got so
in the Palm you will see this parent
block means this is the child P child PR
of what it's a child form of
this so in May one each p. XML is a
child of some other form right if it is
if you have defined this So currently
it's a child of this this project form
so whatever this project so these are
you know that group ID and artifact ID
uniquely identify a particular project
in the mavan
central okay so in this project this is
the version there would be some pom.xml
so that would be parent of this
p parent okay so each P has one
parent if there is no parent defined in
the Palm let's say that if there is no
parent defined in the pal then Mayan
automatically by
default make inherited from a super
P so in Mayan every P which you are
writing right
internally by default it's a child of
super pom.xml
okay so generally in our case in our
PM the p. XML which got download loed in
our project this one which got
downloaded with the
project it is given that it's a child of
this this project so spring boot starter
parent spring
boot some starter parent project it's
pom.xml so this is its parent and this
itself might be a child
of super pom.xml
okay so you got it so this there could
be some other uh there could be some
other parent for this one or if no then
It ultimately would be a child of this
so we can in simple terms we can say
that super p is something which is at
the top of the hierarchy now whatever
the pal you will create whether this or
this generally it's a child of this
super pal
only
okay so the parent used to define the
parent
project current project inherit the
configuration from a specified Pro uh
parent project so our project in is
inherited the configurations from here
so in in our pm. XML if you see this is
very small P right there is not much
configuration why because it might be
using the configuration from its parent
in its parent it might have provided lot
of
configurations right so since it's a
child of it it will use its
configuration whatever its
dependencies all the dependency which
this parent has or the configuration
which parent has all will automatically
comes to your child
also if this parent field is not a
specified Maven by default inherit the
configuration from Super form so this is
the link of the maven super pom I have
provided okay so you can check out the
uh super p. HTML here there are lot of
configurations by default configurations
are available which generally comes to
your project this configuration and
dependencies okay so you understood what
is the meaning of this parent means our
project is generally a child of this
project
actually this three parts I have already
informed you right in the previous uh
when we created this springboard project
group ID artifact ID version these three
uniquely identify our project which we
are creating
so this is the company name generally
you can say this is your ultimately the
project name and this is the version
currently so this uniquely identified
your project in the mavan
central
okay then we have something called
properties so what is properties is it's
a key value pair for
configuration right so this is a
key this is a value
okay
so it can be referenced throughout the
XML file so now in all other XML file I
can use this property this key how let's
say in this dependency group ID artifact
ID and let's say I want to use certain
version I can use like that that let's
say version I can do like this
dollar this java.
version Java do
version close so now this dollar java.
version ultimately what MAV will do it
will check in the properties hey for
this key is there any value defined yes
17 is defined so this will get
ultimately with replaced
with
1710 okay so anything which you define
in properties
it's a generally a key value and then
this key can be referenced anywhere in
the in this
form
okay okay now let's see the next
property which is like
repositories so what does it
do this is from
Mayan look for depend project dependency
and download the artifact jars so here
if you see that in this this repository
we have defined it
one
URL okay so what this URL is this is the
like URL from where you want to download
your dependencies so this is the next if
you see we have a list of
dependencies first is this this is our
first dependency
then this is our second
dependency now from where this
dependency will get
resolved from
this okay so this is where this is from
where MAV look for project dependency
and download the
jars
right so this is generally you can say
that I have written it for you but here
if you see in the project which is
downloaded you will find that this is
missing
this is not
there this is not there generally this
is added uh this is a by default which
Mayan added you can say that maybe in
the super pom.xml you might find that
that this is by default value is present
if you don't add it from its parent P
this will get added so by default it
will always download from mavan Central
only by default so even if you don't
write this maybe if you go and check in
super pom you will find this so that's
why it is not required to add it here
and even in the pom.xml which you
downloaded if you double check you won't
find it because I have added just to
show you that from where it downloaded
the
dependency so till till dependency is
all clear right now actual May one
starts when you see the
build this build element and before I
tell you you about this build you first
need to understand the build life cycle
then only you would be able to
understand why we have to provide this
build what's the usage uh Deep dive into
this but first let's understand the
build life
cycle So Below is the maven build life
cycle so uh let's say that first
is
validate so this first phase is validate
phase what is the second phase second
phase is
compile we will see each phase in depth
but I'm telling you that these are the
sequence first phase second
phase third phase is what
test okay so first it will validate the
project
structure second it will compile the
source code in the the third phase it
will do the testing mean it do unit it
run the test
cases in the fourth phase what it will
do it will package means it will package
the compile code into uh this
jar fifth phase fifth phase is verify it
will verify the Integrity of this
package sixth phase is
install the package into local
repository and the final and the seventh
phase is deploy where it will deploy the
package into the remote
repository so we will see each seven
phes in depth and then after that you
can say that yes you are clear with May
one but one thing you have to say that
these all are sequential
steps let's say that if you want to run
package phase which one is the package
phase fourth
phase then all its previous phase will
also get get executed first so now let's
say if you say that hey I only want to
run this
phase when you give the command to run
this phase
only then all its previous phase first
will get completed this will get
completed first this will get completed
first this will get completed first and
then only this will
run okay so there are you can say that
sequential so there are different phases
right so these are all phases and each
phases has goals multiple goals goals
one goal two there can be different
goals so first phase can have multiple
goals second phase can have multiple
goals so considered goal as nothing but
a task in first phase validate phase
there can be multiple tasks second phase
is your compile phase there can be two
or or three task which it might be doing
right so that's what I have written here
if you want to run a specific task of a
particular phase for example again let's
say for the package inside a
package there are let's say goal
one goal
two goal five let's say there are
multiple goals in the
package this is your phase
4 now let's say that hey I want to
execute this goal and there could be
more goal let's say so this is nothing
but a task which is happening in this
phase okay so you want to perform this
task so to perform this task first it
will goes in sequence it will perform
all the task of this phase all the tasks
all the goals of this phase all the task
of this phase and in the fourth phase it
will perform all the its previous task
this task this task and this
task so got it if you want to do any
particular task if you want to run a
particular task then all its previous
phases and their task will also get
completed if you want to add a specific
task in a specific
phase May provide the functionality or
flexibility to add it let's say that for
example in this
install in the sixth phase what is the
sixth phase is
install there are three tasks task
one task
two task three in the sixth phase of
install this is the phase there are
let's say three tasks now you want that
hey I want to add another task
4 in the in this phase in the install
phase how you can do
it through
build okay so this build element help
you to add a new
task inside one of this phase so this is
the validate first phase is your
validate what validate does this it
validate the project
structure okay so here if you see that
Mayan already has this validate phase
and it is executing his task but if you
want to add more task and we can use
build element and add the goal to a
specific phase so now what is the
command to run the validate May one
validate so now here if you see what I
am doing here I am adding a new plugin I
am adding a new
plug-in this would be inside
build
build close like this inside this build
we are writing a plugins right plugins
and then writing a plugin so I'm writing
a new task here I am writing a new task
here so this is the group ID this is the
artifact ID this Mayan already support
plugin right May has so many plugins you
can either create your own task or you
can already M with supports you can uh
whatever the May One support you can add
it based upon your project need so this
is one
plugin which may One support So in this
these are the coordinates where it will
go and download what task it is now here
if you
see in the
execution we uh this is the task
okay and here if you see this task is
added to which
phase validate
phase okay so Mayan already has this
default phases each phases already has
def uh defined goals which Mayan by
default has it what it has to do but if
you have a requirement to add more tasks
this is how you can do and you can Alo
provide the configuration if any
configuration requirement is to read it
will read this so what ultimately doing
is this plugin this plug-in right what
actually does it it do the check style
it will validate your check style for
example uh my code style.xml there
should be if there should be like a
space between that certain a code check
style so it will validate that that your
code is following a particular check
style or not every company has different
code style some follows this some
follows this right so they want to have
a different structure so you can use
that so you can enforce it here in the
validate phase itself before compiling
itself it will first
validate so you got it the second is
compile compilation of source Cod you
already know what compilation will do
okay so it will convert your Java code
to bite
code do class
files okay so we have to run the command
may1
compile and when we run the mavan
compile you know that it is following a
sequence so even though we are running
this command mavan compile directly this
phase but first it will also complete
the validate phase also
so it will validate and compile your
code and put it under Target classes
we'll show you so now let's say I have
run this command May one
compile so this is the project right on
the same project if I run Mayan
compile then this project what it will
do is so here if you
see this is the phase it is running you
you won't find validate phas you won't
find validate phas because I told you
may one doesn't validate anything like
it doesn't restrict you whatever how you
want to write a code you can write it
but in case you want you can uh add this
plug-in like you can go through and
check different plugins and you can add
for
validate but here if you see when you do
uh may1
compile so this phase runs and what it
does is it generated the it internally
do Java
C now
now understand this I didn't tell I
haven't tell Mayan that do Java C
something I just told him compile Mayan
compile I told him what to do how to do
I didn't tell it but
internally it has this plugins right
so what it will do is it when this
command goes right Mayan
compile so what it will do is it will
Mayan will look for pal. XML and it look
for this Mayan something called compile
plug-in in our P it's not there but
might be in super pom it would be there
so in super pom it would be having
certain coordinates group ID artifact ID
version
so Mayan will use that and fetch
whatever the details it has to fetch so
there Mayan has already provided all the
internally Mayan has already all the
details how to compile the
code whether through Javas or is there
any other way it's their headche we
don't know right but internally it uses
Javas C and it move the classes to this
target so here if you see this is our
project Source main Java this is our
package this is the classes which we
wrote and here and after Mayan
compile you will see new folder comes
into the picture after this test there's
something called target comes in inside
Target classes and if you see that there
are all the dot classes files comes in
so these are the bite code for
this so you got
it
so this is I was saying so previously
ant was popular there we have to tell
what to do and how to do so this is just
one example of how we used to
do like in 20156 like we have to say
that okay compile this is the
project and we have to do
compile where this is the we provide
this is the destination directory where
you have to put the compile code and we
also put that you have to do this Java
C okay so here if you see that we are
providing it that okay you have to
compile so what and here we provide the
command also Java C
how so what and how what both we
provided to the an so read all the files
within this folder put it here how
this
but in Mayan this is abstracted now only
we tell them may1 compile and now this
all this logic is now abstracted within
mavan code base you can say that me
mavan Central it might have certain
plugins so it's like a plugin play that
plugin you
just plug in your form and it will work
okay so third one is test so when you
know that what is the command mavan test
so now when we run this Mayan test you
know that first it will run validate
second it will run compile and then only
it will run
test so it will validate compile and
then run the test cases in your
project so this is our
project right this is the
class and let's say this is the test
class which is inside a test package
I've already told you this is the
structure of m and inside this test
class let's say I have written one unit
test cases this is unit test cases I
have just simply written system. printer
and concept and coding test case
running now I am
running MAV
test so it will do first validate
validate generally Mayan doesn't do
anything and we also haven't added
anything then second it will do
compile it did the compiling and the
third it is running the
test so in compilation it didn't do
anything because nothing to compile
because already everything is compiled
because I have just done the compilation
so already everything is compiled so
that's why it didn't compile that's why
it say that nothing to compile all
classes are up to
date but here it follows the sequence
first it goes to the compile and then
only it comes to the test and then it
run all the test all the uh test cases
unit test cases in inside this folder
and here if you see that concept
encoding test is running it should get
printing over here
somewhere yeah concept encoding test
case running it got printed build
success okay so this phase is clear the
next phase is package the command is May
one package now you know we are trying
to run this phase this phase when it
runs it has to run its previous phases
also what it will do whatever the
compile code which we got right it will
create a jar out of
it first complete validate compile then
test phas and then run the package phase
in which it generates a jar file or bar
file whichever you have selected we have
selected jar in our
springboard so when I run Mayan
package command so so validate is
nothing so this is then it do compile
phase
then test phase this is the test phase
is running and uh test cases ran and
after the test cases it will do the jar
phase this is your
fourth and if you see that where it put
the jar
into so it's building the
jar
into this target here so ear this is our
package right
after compilation and or so after Mayan
package in the Target itself you will
see this jar get
constructed right now this jar you can
share with someone they can add it as a
dependency you can deploy it right so
this now
has everything it's packed everything
whatever is required for our project to
run okay it is bundled of
everything so you got it may one package
what it does it creates a jar and put
into under this target
folder okay after that
package what is the fifth
phase fifth phase is verify May one
verify so generally also here MAV
doesn't force you to verify anything so
might be currently I don't think there
is any task present here it but we can
add it right so let's say my I want I I
want to add one verify phase that I want
to check the Integrity of the package
like so I I want to do static code
analysis a static code analysis like
checks apart from unit test cases
static code analysis means like
uh if there if your if the code has some
unused variable unused import empty
catch block no usage of object duplicate
code I want to find all these things and
report it as a warning or might be
something right so I can add a plug-in
which does all this thing so I can add
it in the verify phase so here if you
see that I am adding a new
plugin so I provided the coordinate to
the MAV hey this is the PMD so PMD has
provided all this
functionality PMD tool can all do all
these things so this is the coordinate
where this PMD we can download the
dependency right and in this PMD this is
the goal this is the task we wanted to
do right out of this plug-in there might
be multiple goals or multiple tasks I
want only this PMD task
so this PMD task does all these
things and I want to put it into which
phase verify
phas okay so how it does this we don't
know some some company or some other
some developer have built this and
deployed it into the MAV and it's open
source we can use it now we are using
this in our code base this is way so we
can provide it
coordinate the task name which they have
given we can tell them okay this is the
task name which we have to perform and
put it into this phase veryy
phase okay now when you do May one
verify what it will do it will first
validate compile test package and then
run the check for all this issues if it
find anything then it will report
you okay your sixth phase is
install command is Mayan
install so when you do the
install you have validated your code you
have your bite code do class file you
have run the test cases you have Do jar
file right currently in the Target
folder do you have also verified that
everything is good there is no static
analysis or if you want you can add more
verify like check some signature
anything right so verification is also
done now you want to install install
means you want to install the package
this jar file into the local
repository Now understand this what is
local repository so in May
one this is something that this
is your system so let's say
me so this is
me this is my
system okay and let's say this
is Mayan
Central this is
public okay this is where so many
repositories are
available okay
so whatever this jar file is created
there is something called local
repository here in my system so local
repository is lies where is in my system
okay and this is when this jar file I
have to deploy it somewhere outside my
system that is known as remote
repository so let's say in this case
Mayan Central can be your remote
repository if you are working in a
company
then you are within a
network where your company has managing
your remote
repository so whatever the jar file you
will upload it will get uploaded here
not to the Mayan which is
public it will get so this is your
remote but in simple terms local
repository is something
in your own
system right and remote repository is
something is outside of your system I
will tell you how you can configure that
whether I should be using this and my
company someware repository or mayavan
Central repository how to do that I'll
tell
you
but what it will do package what this
mayavan install Mayan install will do it
will install the DOT jar package Do jar
package into the local M
repository which is typically located in
your user home directory if you are
using a Mac then it will goes under
here right so your home then M2 folder
will get created and repository so when
you will download may1 right when you
will download Mayan right then you will
find that this Mayan will create
this repository this folder this path
will create so whenever you do
install so it will deploy the it will
install this dot jar package inside this
path and this path you can configure you
can change it right so there is
something called
settings.xml in this M2 folder itself in
this M2 folder there is something
called settings.xml file in the
settings.xml file there is something
called local repository so you can
change this path then whenever you do
MAV install right so all your
dependencies uh all your jar package
will goes to that path not to this
path okay so here is like this is the
generally the structure so whenever you
download the Mayan you will see that M2
folder is also created in your
homepage inside M2 you will find
settings.xml and also you will find a
repository folder okay currently you
will find only this this three
M2 repository folder and settings.xml
that's all now when you will run M
install when you run MAV install what it
will do is it will copy all the depend
this
jar into this path and it will follow
the path so it will create like com
concept and coding learning spring boot
like your the proper hierarchy it will
make and then it will ultimately put the
snapshot jar file so earlier it was
present under Target right during
package so during MAV install it will
put into this my local repository this
is local
Repository
and this path I don't want to put into
under repository I want to create some
other folder might say my folder my
folder and I want it to put it here you
can change it in the
settings.xml you can change the path of
the local repository or give whatever
the path you wanted so the jar file will
goes into that
one
okay
so here now here I'm
doing may1
install so it will do first
validate then it will do second
compile then it will run test cases
after running test cases what it will do
it will do the package right it
will do the
package after running the package it
will do verify I think we don't have
verify and after that it do
install so it do sequence of stop and
during install whatever the Jal file was
created as part of first uh this MAV
package it will use that jar file and
put it
into from Target from
Target to your local repository path M2
repository concept encoding this path it
will put
it okay
and if you want to change it you can
change it in settings.xml so whenever
you download a M1 this M2 folder will be
created repository will be created
settings will be created settings.xml
and you can change it uh as
required okay got
it so now whenever so now you have local
repository and then you know that there
is something called remote
repository remote repository remote
repository could be your company or the
mavan central so
whenever you have to download any
dependency your pal. XML
Mayan Mayan will first will give
preference to local repository it will
check hey in the local repository do I
have this dependency or not if that
dependency is not there
then it will goes to remote repository
downloaded it and put it into the
local now in again in future when it has
to look then it will look to the remote
uh local and it will automatically find
it because it has already been put in
the previous step
itself so you got it so that's why local
repository you can say that it helps so
that we can avoid calling remote
repository again and again do during
dependency resolution
also and the last step here in this is
the seventh phase is deploy the command
is MAV deploy and now you know that when
you are doing this mavan deploy command
even if you running this all this phases
will run
also but what it will do is it will
deploy the dot jar file to remote
repository now remote repository could
could be
your
company
Central or could be
Mayan public which is public it's
Central whichever you will Define I will
tell you how you can Define it so in the
pal.
XML you have to define something like
this distribution
management okay distribution management
inside distribution management you have
to tell
repository where it has to deploy your
remote repository
URL okay so if you see in your company
the pal which we have got in our form
the dependency management is not there
because it consider that we don't have
to deploy it's just our internal
learning purpose so we don't have to
deploy our code to M Central or
something so we don't have this but if
you want to deploy so you have to put
the URL where you have to deploy in if
you are working in a company then check
your company's form you will you will
find that you have provided your
company's URL here so whenever you do
May one deploy it will goes to your
company Central
somewhere right and you for connecting
it you might need to provide the
username password also right because we
can't just connect to any URL and upload
the
jar file there you have to authenticate
yourself so the the username password
generally we put into
settings.xml in the settings.xml there
is something called server you can add
and in that the ID is your remote
repository ID and the username password
you can give remote repository username
and
password so with this username password
it can connect to your uh this URL and
it will upload the jar there
but there is no default Mayan provide so
if you for our code here if you see that
you won't find any dependency management
you won't find any dist uh not
dependency distribution management you
won't find any distribution management
and remote repository if you run the M
deploy for our current project right you
will face the below error build failure
why deployment failure repository
element was not specified in the form
inside distribution management
element so you have to add it so now
let's say that if you don't want to
deploy this uh jar to your company or
something you want to deploy it to the
Mayan Mayan Central you can provide the
Mayan Central URL and for Mayan Central
URL no there is no need for username and
password because it's public there is no
username password you can keep it
empty right so this is is the URL for
the mayavan central if I add this
distribution Management in our pal right
and run this Mayan deploy it will I can
uh deploy it to the Mayan Central then
you also can download that from Mayan
with this group ID artifact ID version
this is the coordinate you can now once
it go to the mavan central anybody can
download this then
you got it okay guys thank you bye